# Ellis L. Brown, II

**\** 314.761.1662 • ☑ ellisbrown@cmu.edu • � ellisbrown.github.io **in** ellislbrownii • **②** google scholar • **♀** ellisbrown

## Interests

My research interests lie at the intersection of deep learning, computer vision, and robotics. I am particularly interested in *self-supervised learning*, representation learning, and open-ended/continual learning with application to robot learning & RL. I am keen to draw inspiration from intelligence in nature/humans. My goal is to develop agents that use common sense to efficiently *generalize* to the complexities of the real world.

## **Education**

Carnegie Mellon University

M.S., Computer Science; Advised by Professors Deepak Pathak and Alexei Efros

Stanford University

Non-Degree Graduate Student, Computer Science

Columbia University

Non-Degree Graduate Student, Computer Science

Vanderbilt University

B.S., Computer Science; B.A., Mathematics; Advised by Professor Maithilee Kunda

Pittsburgh, PA

(expected) May 2023

Palo Alto, CA

Jun. 2020

New York, NY

May 2019

Nashville, TN

May 2017

## **Publications**

2023 A. Li\*, **E. Brown**\*, A. Efros, D. Pathak. *Internet Explorer: Representation Learning on the Open Web. CVPR 2023* (under review)

A. Li\*, E. Brown\*, A. Efros, D. Pathak. Internet Curiosity: Directed Unsupervised Learning on Uncurated Internet Data. ECCV 2022, Workshop on "Self Supervised Learning: What is Next?" Tel Aviv, Isr. (Poster)

2018 **E. Brown**, S. Park, N. Warford, A. Seiffert, K. Kawamura, J. Lappin, and M. Kunda. An Architecture for Spatiotemporal Template-Based Search. *Advances in Cognitive Systems, Volume 6*, 101-118.

2018 **E. Brown**, S. Park, N. Warford, A. Seiffert, K. Kawamura, J. Lappin, and M. Kunda. SpatioTemporal Template-based Search: An Architecture for Spatiotemporal Template-Based Search. *Sixth Annual Conference on Advances in Cognitive Systems*, Stanford, CA. (Oral)

## **Awards and Honors**

Scholar, Lighting the Pathways to Faculty Careers for Natives in STEM, AISES
Intel Growing the Legacy Graduate Scholarship
Scholar, Computer Science Research Mentorship Program, Google Research
3<sup>rd</sup> Place, Graduate Student Research Competition, AISES National Conference
Osage Nation Higher Education Scholarship
(2x) Academic All-American, USA Water Polo
2021–2017; 2021–2017
2013–2017; 2021–2018

## **Experience**

#### Robotics Institute, Carnegie Mellon University

Graduate Student Researcher, Advised by Professors Deepak Pathak and Alexei Efros

2022-Pres.

- Researching self-supervised learning, curiosity-driven exploration, and generalization.
- Lead contributor to securing a \$30m cross-institutional DARPA Machine Common Sense grant for CMU, UC Berkeley, MIT, and UMich—team "MESS" (Model-building, Exploratory, Social-learning Systems).

#### BlackRock AI Labs

Advised by Professors Mykel Kochenderfer, Stephen Boyd, and Trevor Hastie.

Founding team member and culture carrier. Launched bi-weekly reading group. Co-launched external website.

<sup>\*</sup>equal contribution

Research Engineer | Palo Alto, CA

2020-2021

- Formulated the securities lending process as a Markov decision process; designed and wrote a multi-agent lending market simulator for the learning and evaluation of policies; showed that learned policies outperform the rule-based policy used by the lending desk.
- Open-sourced two Julia packages for separable optimization problems. Presented at JuliaCon 2021. [blog, talk]

Machine Learning Engineer | New York, NY

2018-2019

- Proposed a model of portfolio "operational risk," decomposable into interpretable factors. Built a Spark ETL pipeline that extracts 3k+ features from systems across the firm and outputs daily predictions for every managed portfolio.
- Designed a system to automatically parse compliance rules from legal documents; previously performed by 30 FTEs.

#### BlackRock

Software Engineer | New York, NY

2017

• Built an ETL pipeline to ingest daily mutual fund reference data using Apache Storm.

Software Engineering Intern | New York, NY

2016

• Won intern hackathon with NLP system to extract contract terms from legal documents during new client onboarding.

#### Department of Computer Science, Vanderbilt University

Undergraduate Student Researcher, Advised by Professor Maithilee Kunda

2016-2018

- Developed a computational cognitive architecture of human attention during spatiotemporal visual search.
- Contributed to the development of the Toybox Dataset for small sample learning and hand-object interaction.

#### Open-Source.....

JuliaFirstOrder/{ PiecewiseQuadratics.jl, SeparableOptimization.jl }

2021

• Co-authored Julia packages for solving the problem of minimizing a sum of piecewise-quadratic functions subject to affine equality constraints via a derivative of the Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers (ADMM). Formed the JuliaFirstOrder organization.

amdegroot/ssd.pytorch

★ 4.7k \$ 1.7k

• Co-authored the canonical PyTorch implementation of the Single Shot MultiBox Detector, a real-time object detection framework using a single network, 3 months after PyTorch's alpha release.

#### Teaching

## **Department of Computer Science**

Vanderbilt University

Teaching Assistant, CS 2201: Program Design & Data Structures

Fall 2015

• Held weekly office hours for class of 200+ students. Graded weekly progamming assignments and exams.

## **Talks**

- 2021 Linearly Constrained Separable Optimization (oral), JuliaCon 2021 JuMP-dev track. [talk]
- Modeling Uncertainty in Bayesian Neural Networks with Dropout: the effect of weight prior and 2019 network architecture selection (poster), American Indian Science and Engineering Society National Conference 2019, Madison, WI. [poster]
- 2018 SpatioTemporal Template-based Search: An Architecture for Spatiotemporal Template-Based Search (oral), Sixth Annual Conference on Advances in Cognitive Systems, Stanford, CA. [slides]
- 2017 Computational Cognitive Systems to Model Information Salience (oral), American Indian Science and Engineering Society National Conference 2017, Denver, CO. [slides, link]

#### Graduate Coursework

CMU: Deep RL for Robotics, Visual Learning & Recognition, Deep RL & Control, Advanced Intro ML, Philosophical Foundations of Machine Intelligence, Math Fundamentals for Robotics, Distributed Systems, Intro to Computer Systems Stanford: Engineering Design Optimization Columbia: Mathematics of Deep Learning

2022 Alvin Shek, Ellis Brown, Nilay Pande, David Noursi. Self-Supervised Representation Learning via Curiosity-Driven Exploration. Robotics Institute, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA. [report]

- 2021 **Ellis Brown**, Aaron M. Roth. Scaling Interpretable Reinforcement Learning via Decision Trees to Minecraft. Robotics Institute, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA. [report]
- 2020 **Ellis Brown**. Securities Lending Policy Optimization. Computer Science Department, Stanford University, Palo Alto, CA. [report, video]
- 2019 Ellis Brown\*, Melanie Manko\*, Ethan Matlin\*. Modeling Uncertainty in Bayesian Neural Networks with Dropout. Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Columbia University, New York, NY. [report, slides]

## **Extracurricular Activities**

## American Indian Science & Engineering Society (AISES)

Volunteer 2019–2021

- Mentored an undergraduate AISES student studying CS through the 2020-2021 Full Circle Mentorship Program.
- Reviewed scholarships for the 2020 AISES Undergraduate Scholarship.
- Judged posters for Undergraduate Student Research Competition at the 2019 National Conference.

## Code/Interactive

Mentor 2018

Advised and tutored (weekly) an underprivileged high schooler interested in CS; helped prepare college applications.

#### Vanderbilt Admissions

Tour Guide 2014–2016

• Led weekly campus tours to groups of 10-50+ prospective students and families.

### Kappa Sigma Fraternity (Kappa Chapter)

Social Chairman 2014–2016

• Managed \$90k annual budget; planned & executed dozens of large-scale events; served on Executive Council.

#### Water Polo

Captain & President, Vanderbilt Club Team (2014 SEC Champions)

2014-2016

• Coordinated and led a team of 20+ players through a 10 week season with 2+ travel tournaments.

#### Trainee, USA Olympic Development Program

2010-2013

• Trained in the United States National Team Pipeline program. Competed in Junior Olympics.

<sup>\*</sup>equal contribution